A Finding Aid to the Aleksandra Kasuba Papers, 1942-2013, bulk 1960-2000, in the Archives of American Art AAA.kasualek
Archives of American Art
Aleksandra Kasuba papers
bulk 1960-2000
1942-2013
AAA.kasualek
Archives of American Art
5.6 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor and environmental artist Aleksandra Kasuba measure 5.6 linear feet and date from 1942-2013, with the bulk of the material from 1960-2000. The collection documents Kasuba's career through biographical material, correspondence, interviews, lectures and writings, extensive project files, printed material, a scrapbook, artwork, and photographs.
Kasuba, Aleksandra, 1923-
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2013 by Aleksandra Kasuba.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
Aleksandra Kasuba (1923-), a Lithuanian-born sculptor, best known for her innovative architectural environments has lived in New York and New Mexico. She attended the Kaunas Art Institute and the Academy of Fine Arts in Vilnius, Lithuania from 1941-1943. She studied with the sculptor, Vytautus Kasuba, whom she married in 1944. In response to the Soviet Army's occupation of their country, Aleksandra Kasuba and her husband emigrated to the United States in 1947. By 1963, Aleksandra Kasuba, her husband, and two children had moved to the Upper West Side in New York City. At the start of her career, Kasuba received commissions to make ceramic tiles for use in furniture. About the same time, she was also collaborating with architects in designing mosaic wall installations for public works. Aleksandra Kasuba's commissioned projects have included a plaza on Pennsylvania Avenue, Washington, D.C., and wall mosaics for the Container Corporation in Chicago, and 560 Lexington Avenue in New York City. Some of Kasuba's mosaic compositions were made as individual pieces to be included in museum and gallery exhibitions.
Aleksandra Kasuba has also devoted her career to designing alternative living environments. In the late 1960s, Kasuba built dwellings that she referred to as Space Shelters, which were made from a fabric of her own design. In 1970, the American Craft Museum featured Kasuba's tensile-fabric structure in an exhibition "Contemplative Environments." She has also used nylon fabric to build her alternative or live-in environments. In addition, Kasuba has held several faculty positions. She taught at the School of Visual Arts in New York City from 1971-1972 and was an artist-in-residence at Cranbrook Academy of Art in 1976 and the Philadelphia College of Textiles & Science in 1977. Kasuba has received awards from the American Institute of Architects in 1971 and 1972; in 1983, she was granted a Fellowship from the National Endowment for the Arts. Aleksandra Kasuba has written several books, including a memoir published in 2001. Kasuba's husband, Vytautus died in 1997. Since 2001, Aleksandra Kasuba has been living in Albuquerque, New Mexico, where she purchased a tract of land in the desert to continue her work on experimental housing.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 9 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1969-2005 (Box 1; 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1967-1998 (Box 1; 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 3: Interviews, 1976-1983 (Box 1; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 4: Lectures and Writings, circa 1976-1986 (Box 1; 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 5: Project Files, 1960-2013 (Boxes 1-4; 3.1 linear ft.)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1950-1988 (Box 5; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 7: Scrapbook, 1971-2010 (Box 6; 1 folder)
Series 8: Artwork, circa 1943-2001 (Boxes 5-6; 0.6 linear ft.)
Series 9: Photographs, 1942-1949 (Boxes 5, 7; 0.7 linear ft.)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of sculptor and environmental artist Aleksandra Kasuba measure 5.6 linear feet and date from 1942-2013, with the bulk of the material from 1960-2000. The collection documents Kasuba's career through biographical material, correspondence, interviews, lectures and writings, extensive project files, printed material, a scrapbook, artwork, and photographs.
Biographical material contains artist's statements, biographical data, letters of recommendation, and a citation from the American Institute of Architects. General correspondence mostly consists of invitations to lecture at academic institutions and professional associations. There are letters between Kasuba and interior design firms, publishers, museums, and academic institutions. Included are letters from Columbia University, Museum of Modern Art, and the Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies. Correpondence relates to commissioned projects, proposed exhibitions, and the scheduling of workshops and speaking engagements. Also found is correspondence with Thomas Whitridge about the publication of a monograph by Kasuba.
The collection includes three interviews with Kasuba and a panel discussion between the artist and Nina Freudenheim. There is a transcript of a 1976 interview by Jerilyn Berlind. Lectures and writings include draft lectures and an essay on art by Kasuba. Included is a typescript of an article about Kasuba's work.
Extensive project files provide detailed documentation on Kasuba's installations, exhibitions, and space shelters mainly from 1960-1990. Included are a variety of materials: correspondence, proposals, contracts and agreements, sketches of models, clippings, photographs, and motion picture films of work. Also found are files relating Kasuba's book projects and her participation in symposia and competitions.
Printed material includes exhibition catalogs, announcements, and brochures; news and magazine clippings document various projects, including Kasuba's wall mosaics, shell dwellings, and alternative living environments. A scrapbook consists mainly of news clippings and reviews on Kasuba's work.
Artwork consists of sketches and drawings used as preliminary designs for Kasuba's projects. Photographs are of Kasuba's wall mosaics, reliefs, space shelters, and live-in environments. Also found are slides and three slide binders of wall installations, shell dwellings, and environments made of tensile fabrics; included are slides used for lectures.
Berlind, Jerilyn; Columbia University.; Freudenheim, Nina; Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.).; Whitridge, Thomas; Drawings; Environmental artists; Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sculptors--New Mexico; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York; Sketches; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Women artists
- Biographical Material, circa 1969-2005; Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes artist's statements and letters of recommendation. Biographical data consists of curriculum vitae, bibliographies, checklists of commissioned work and biographical entries; also found are drafts of biographical accounts used for press releases. Included is a citation to Kasuba from the Women's Architectural Auxiliary, New York Chapter of the American Institute of Architects in honor of her participation in a West Side urban renewal project.
  Arrangement note
  Files are arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
  - Artist's Statements, 1977-1989; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Data, circa 1969-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Citation, American Institute of Architects, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1967-1998; Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet Box 1
  This series includes scattered letters from professional associations, academic institutions, and interior design firms inviting Kasuba to lecture or participate in a workshop. Correspondence includes project and exhibition proposals as well as several requests to reproduce her work. There are letters recommending Kasuba for teaching positions. Correspondents include the Architectural League of New York, Columbia University, Museum of Modern Art, and University of Cincinnati. Attachments to letters include biographical material, outlines of courses, lists of projects completed, sketches of plans, printed material, and images of exhibition installations. Correspondence with Thomas Whitridge of Didymus Press relates to the publication of Kasuba's Utility of the Soul: The Retreat House; also included are copies of the monograph.
  Files are arranged in original order. There were two filing systems for correspondence: general correspondence and correspondence by subject and name of individual or organization. Letters are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - General Correspondence, 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Proposals, 1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Thomas Whitridge, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Museum of Modern Art, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Teaching Positions, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Interviews, 1976-1983; Series 3; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  This series includes three formal interviews with Aleksandra Kasuba. There are transcripts of a 1976 interview with Kasuba and of the artist's interview with Design Magazine. Also included is a recorded discussion between Aleksandra Kasuba and Nina Freudenheim held at Buffalo State University. Recordings are on two videocassettes and one sound cassette.
  Files are arranged in chronological order.
  - Interview with Aleksandra Kasuba, 1976; Transcript only. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interview with Design Magazine, 1976-1977; 1 videocassette (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Interview for National Public Radio "Fresh Air", 1978; 1 Sound cassettes Note found with original box (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Panel Discussion with Aleksandra Kasuba and Nina Freudenheim (1983 October 13), 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Lectures and Writings, circa 1976-1986; Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet Box 1
  This series includes Aleksandra Kasuba's lectures on the effects of alternative living environments on human behavior presented at academic forums and corporations. Writings include an essay by Kasuba and a typescript of an article on Kasuba that was published in Woman's Art Journal (Fall 1988/Winter 1984).
  Recordings are on one sound cassette and one videocassette.
  - Various Lectures, circa 1976-1985; Includes 1 sound cassette. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lecture, "A Soft Form," Georgia State University, circa 1980; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Aleksandra Kasuba, "Thoughts on Nature, Structure and Art", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mary Lee Thompson, "Aleksandra Kasuba's Plaza for the Old Post Office", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Project Files, 1960-2013; Series 5; 3.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-4
  The bulk of the series documents Kasuba's installations, exhibitions, tensile-fabric dwellings and live-in environments. Included are correspondence, artist's statements, project notes, plans, sketches and diagrams, business-related materials including agreements and cost estimates, printed material, clippings, and exhibition installation photographs and slides of artwork. There are files on Aleksandra Kasuba's professional activities, including teaching positions, speaking engagements, and publishing projects.
  In addition, recordings include 13 electronic discs (DVD), one super 8 mm film reel and two 8 mm motion picture film reels.
  - "Stations of the Cross" - Franciscan Monastery, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Stone and Marble Mosaics and Commissions, 1960-1963; 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Broad Street National Bank, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - New York Hilton, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Black Marble Mosaics, 2012; 1965-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Bank of California - Fixed Art Program, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rochester Institute of Technology - Brick Mural, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Container Corporation - Mosaic Tile Wall Murals, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Baltimore High School, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Work Leading to Environments, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Work Leading to Environments - How it Was Done, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Work Leading to New Mexico - Waterfront, 1969-1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Show Constructs, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Spiral, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "The Four Elements" and "The Spectrum Environment", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Global Village, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 43 West 90th Street, New York Environment - Proposal, Drawings, and Plans, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Responses to 43 West 90th Street, New York Environment, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Live-In Environment in a Floor Through of A Brownstone, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Seagram Project/Marilyn Ward (1972 September 29) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Whiz Bang Quick City 2, Woodstock, New York, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "The 20th Century Environment," The Carborundum Museum of Ceramics, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
  - Mixed Media - Environments, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - New York Department of Water Resources, East Bronx Repair Headquarters, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lincoln Hospital, Bronx, New York, 1972-1980; Includes 1 electronic disc (DVD). (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Center for Environmental Studies - Wave Hill, New York, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Color Structures, Potsdam, New York, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Manhattan Community Rehabilitation Center - Roof Deck, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28-31)
  - "The Rainbow Show," De Young Memorial Museum, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - Patent Lawyer's Report - Structure Utilizing Expandable Mesh Reinforcement, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reading Study Center - University of Delaware, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Lepercq Office Renovation, New York, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Millay Colony for the Arts, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Spectral Passage - De Young Memorial Museum, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Yale University Dramatic Association, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Book, 1977; undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Elaine Summers - Experimental Intermedia Foundation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Workshop Proposals, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Art-in-Science I - Philadelphia College of Textiles and Science, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
  - The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey - Waterwall, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - University City Science Center and the Philadelphia College of Textiles - Tensile Fabric Structures for Dwellings, 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - University City Science Center and the Philadelphia College of Textiles - Proposals to Build Shell Dwellings, 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Blue Shade," Jacob Riis National Park, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Sun Screen, Filmed by Pola Chapelle (1978 June 20), 1 Film reels Super 8 mm (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Suspended Structure - Colony Square, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Old Post Office Plaza, Washington, D.C., 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - 560 Lexington Avenue, New York - Brick Sculpture, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Paris and the 20th Century Environment, circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Prototypes and Future Building Methods Leading to New Mexico, circa 1980-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Showrooms in Paris, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Expo-Creations Paris, France/CRS Group + Metcalf & Eddy, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - New Dorp High School, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Amherst Station - Art Brickwork, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Modular Design System - Proposal No. 1, circa 1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Helen Drutt - Women's Caucus for Art, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - One James Plaza, Richmond, Virginia, 1984-1986; 2013 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Bronx District 6 Sanitation Garage, 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Frei Otto, 1984-1990 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Art-in-Transit Program - Plaza Pavement Design, Wilshire/Alvarado Stations, Los Angeles, California, 1984-1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Portable Kiosk, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - World Trade Center - East Wall, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
  - Minimal Surfaces, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Art-in-Science Project - University City Science Center, 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - New York Waterfront, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Knoxville Museum of Art at the Candy Factory, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Shaping the Future - Art-in-Science VII, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
  - Book - KasubaWorks, Quarx Press Files, circa 2000; 12 Electronic discs (DVD) includes duplicates (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Spectral Environment - Adaptation for National Gallery, Vilnius, Lithuana, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Unidentified Project Files, undated; 2 Film reels 8 mm (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Unlabeled films appear to be documentation of artworks.
- Printed Material, 1950-1988; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 5
  Printed material contains some news and magazine clippings, brochures, announcements, an invitation and a monograph. Exhibition catalogs feature Kasuba's installations and include a rare copy of A Report on the Art and Technology Program of the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1967-1971.
  Files are arranged by document type.
  - News Clippings, 1950-1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reviews of Aleksandra Kasuba's Installations, 1960-1984 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1970-1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Announcements/Invitation, 1975-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Brochures, 1977-circa 1982 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Book - Underground Interiors: Decorating for Alternative Life Styles, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Scrapbook, 1971-2010; Series 7
  This series consists of one scrapbook of news clippings and reviews of Aleksandra Kasuba's projects and exhibitions with a few letters and loose clippings on several habitats designed by Kasuba in New Mexico.
  - Scrapbook, 1971-2010 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Oversized material housed in Box 6
  - Oversized Scrapbook from Box 5, Folder 7
- Artwork, circa 1943-2001; Series 8; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 5-6
  This series includes Kasuba's sketches and designs used as models for shell dwellings and environments made from tensile fabric. Also found are figure, portrait, landscape and genre studies by Kasuba that were done early in her career.
  Files are arranged by subject.
  - Figure, Portrait, Landscape, and Genre Studies, undated; 1943-1952 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Mosaics, circa 1943-circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Lepercq Office Renovation, circa 1974-circa 1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Futuristic Building Method, 1971-1977 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Villages and Township, 1971-1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Stretched Shell Housing, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Buildings, 1986-1989 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Plans for Saint Francis Chapel, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - California, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Main House - New Mexico, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Oversized Figure, Portrait, Landscape, and Genre Studies from Box 5, Folder 8 (Box 6)
  - Oversized Mosaics from Box 5, Folder 9 (Box 6)
  - Oversized Lepercq Office Renovation from Box 5, Folder 10 (Box 6)
  - Oversized Plans for Saint Francis Chapel from Box 5, Folder 15 (Box 6)
- Photographs, 1942-1949; 1960s-2000; Series 9; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 5,7
  Photographs and slides are of Aleksandra Kasuba’s mosaics, shell dwellings, and environments. Found are three binders of slides of artwork and installation projects; binder 3 includes 6 electronic discs (CD).
  Researchers should note that photographs are also found within Series 5: Project Files. This series is arranged by format and thereafter in chronological format.
  - Beginnings, Mosaics, and Reliefs, undated; 1960s-2000; 1942 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Grass Works, circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Oversized material housed in Box 7
  - Live-In Environment, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Buildings, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - First Dwelling Model, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Slides - Beginnings, Mosaics, and Reliefs, 1949-1989 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Slides - Best-of-Fruit Sequence, circa 1980-circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Slides - Duplicate Set Sent to Frei Otto (1984 December) (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Slide Binder 1: Artwork, 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Slide Binder 2: Not-So-Still Life, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Slide Binder 3: Installation Projects, 1971-1989; Includes 6 electronic discs (CD). (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Oversized Grass Works from Box 5, Folder 19 (Box 7)
  - Oversized Live-In Environment from Box 5, Folder 20 (Box 7)